[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
se-radio.net. SE radio is brought to you
by the ITE computer society and by it e
software magazine online at
[Music]
computer.org/software. Welcome to
software engineering radio. I'm your
host Gregory Caphammer. Today's guest is
Aaron Yohov. He's the CTO of Tab 9 and a
faculty member in the computer science
department at the Israel Institute of
Technology. Erin, welcome to Software
Engineering Radio. Hey, great to be
here. Thank you for having me. Today
we're going to be talking about the Tab
9 AI coding assistant. It uses large
language models to help software
engineers complete tasks like code
explanation and test case generation.
Aaron, are you ready to dive into the
episode? I'm definitely ready. Yeah. All
right. So, one of the things I noticed
on the Tab 9 website is that it has a
million monthly users. First of all,
congratulations. That's really cool.
What I want to do now is to talk a
little bit about what those Tab 9 users
are doing. Can you give a few concrete
examples of how software engineers use
Tab 9? Yeah, sure. So, the Tab 9
provides assistance across the entire
SDLC. It helps you write code with code
completions that are very advanced. It
has a chat interface that allows you to
create new code, review code, refactor
code, translate between languages,
generate tests as you mentioned
initially, document code, explain it. So
it basically helps you do anything that
you have to do as a software engineer.
And the vision is really to provide
agents that help you do anything and
everything a software engineer does just
faster and with a higher quality. So you
mentioned that it helps software
engineers both move more rapidly and
also do things with better quality.
What's the reason that Tab 9 helps that
to happen? I guess there's so much
boilerplate and so much boring work in
code generation in programming. We know
that and for years people have been
obviously copying snippets from past
projects from Stack Overflow, from the
internet at large just to get over these
boring things and get over with it and
then you basically get whatever is out
there. you know with the rise of LMS and
with the rise of assistants like top 9
that can contextualize deeply on your
context on your organization's code etc.
uh you have the opportunity to generate
these piece of code much more
efficiently and more I guess true to
what they should be in your context
right so part of the quality of the code
that you're generating is being suitable
for the environment in which you're
operating and I think this is one
particular aspect that Tab 9 excels with
so later in our episode we'll dive into
the specifics of Tab 9's implementation
and how software engineers can use it.
Before we do that, at a high level, can
you explain a little bit about how Tab 9
actually automatically performs these
tasks? Yeah, sure. So, at the bottom of
the whole thing are obviously large
language models, right? LMS and they are
capable of doing amazing things these
days. They're very powerful and they're
becoming more powerful on a weekly basis
almost. But from the LM to an actual use
as a software engineer, there's a hole
that has to happen in the middle, right?
Part of that is the context that I
mentioned earlier. So top 9 has what we
call the enterprise context engine which
is something that basically knows how to
draw relevant context from all code
sources of information and non-code
source of information in the
organization to make sure that again top
9 operates like an onboarded employee of
the organization and not as a foreign
engineer in the org. So top 9 knows
everything about the org and which
informs the code that it generates, how
it reviews code etc etc. The second
thing that is there between the LM and
the agents is a component that provides
trust. One of the major questions that
we ask ourselves as engineers when we
delegate a task to AI or even to a
junior engineer is how can we trust the
results that we get back, right? And
Tub9 really focuses on that with
something that we call coaching. Top 9
coaching. And that allows top 9 to make
sure that the code being generated and
code being pushed into your codebase
follow organizational specific rules of
what does it mean to be high quality
code? What does mean to follow
organizational best practices etc. So
again, we can and will talk about the
technical detail of how these things are
done later. But if you're trying to look
like for 30 ft view, 30,000 ft view
here, it's more LM contextual context,
organizational context, trust and agents
that are built on top of that. Okay,
that was really helpful. We're going to
dive in more to the issues about trusts
and the specific LLMs that are used by
Tab 9. Before we do that, I wanted to
just get a highlevel perspective of the
various features. Maybe if I could read
off a feature and then you could briefly
describe it, we might be able to give
the listeners a fullfeatured picture of
some of the things that Tab 9 provides.
So, you talked about this already. Let's
revisit code generation. How does code
generation work in Tab 9? Yeah. So in
the old days as I call it which old days
meaning like two years ago maybe that's
like ancient history like this is akin
to Roman empire in terms of AI for
software engineering most of the users
were really using code completions to
generate code and it could be either
code completion just from typing you
know the prefix and getting tab 9 to
complete what you're typing or typing a
natural language comment and getting
code generated off that progressively I
think or increasingly People are using
more and more the chat interface to
generate larger amounts of code. Even
code that crosses file boundaries,
different places in the projects that
have to be updated. So you can just
describe what is it that you're trying
to do as a very high level prompt and
top 9 will generate the code, do the
whatever modifications required for you.
And I think we're seeing more and more
code being generated that way. Thanks
for that description of code generation.
I'm operating under the assumption that
Tab 9 can also generate the
documentation for the code. Is that
correct? Yeah, absolutely. Generating
documentation to me when we started
sounded a bit off because, you know,
I've been taught that documentation
should describe why things were done and
not what or how they're doing it, right?
But turns out that first of all, it's
better to have some documentation than
none. And second, once you get time to
generate some documentation, turns out
that developers are actually completing
the part that is, you know, some the
extra information that only the human
knows maybe. So it's different writing
documentation from scratch versus, hey,
Tab 9 already generated the bulk of it.
Let me just add a couple of sentences
here that clarify for a run of the
future why this was done this way. So it
sounds like tab 9 can generate both
documentation for the code it's
generating and it can also generate
documentation for existing code in your
codebase. Yeah, absolutely. Yeah. Okay.
Now a moment ago you seem to hint at
something which looked like a larger
scale change. So how does Tab 9 support
things like largecale code changes or
system refactoring? Yeah, system
refactoring. I think we're not quite
there yet. I think large scale changes,
changes across multiple files, edits
that take into account existing
microservices in the organization and
edits that refer to code that exist
elsewhere in the org. These are all
things that are enabled by the top N
context engine. And again, I think it's
quite remarkable and surprising the kind
of things that we can do right now by
prompting tab 9 or assistants in general
and getting them to make changes across
I don't know tens of files in the
project changes that are consistent and
compile and run right so that's I think
something that happened really in the
past year or so that progress I expect
that to keep improving So we can make
changes across the entire or maybe
refactoring across the entire org.
Thanks for that response. I heard you
say a moment ago that tab 9 operates in
an agentic fashion. Can you explain what
that is? The agentic fashion for us
varies for different levels of autonomy.
You know, at a high level, we mean
something that has a higher degree of
autonomy than just a human AI
conversation of like a request response
or chat question and answer, right? We
mean something, for example, that can
say, "Hey, Tub 9, generate all the tests
required to reach a certain code
coverage target." Or, "Hey, Tub 9, why
don't you give me a test plan for
something and then implement it, right?
So things that are multi-stage and quite
sophisticated and involve planning and
you don't know up front for example how
many iterations it requires with the LM
and things like that again we can get
into like technical definitions of all
those things later but just to give the
intuition we're talking about things
that have a higher degree of autonomy
than just a conversation okay so if I'm
working in a way that there's less
autonomy I might be for example writing
code and tab 9 will complete completed
or I might ask Tab 9 to generate a test
or generate documentation but as I give
it more autonomy it's taking on more of
the tasks for me. Is that the right way
to think about it? Yeah, that's the
right way to think about it. In general,
you know, people talk about coding
assistants versus agents versus AI
engineer. And there's not much of a
dichotomy there. It's actually a
continuum, right? As we increase the
level of autonomy in every task and as
we increase the percentage of tasks that
can be completed by AI, we are getting
closer and closer to the AI engineer.
And I think the challenge is to do that
in a way that continuously provides
value to the developer and still
maintains the trust in the delegation.
Right? It's all about delegation. the AI
assistance or the AI engineer is a
matter of delegation. So if you think
about code completion that was kind of a
micro delegation, right? I typed
something I did not have to specify
anything because the specification was
implicit. The prefix and the context
were the specification, right? And then
tab 9 completes it. So that's a micro
delegation. And the question of trust is
also quite simple. It's very tight. You
mean the loop trust. you Greg look at
the completion and say oh yeah these
three lines look great that's exactly
what I would have written myself or hey
let me think about it for a second
that's not what I would have written but
it looks correct so let me take that so
that's kind of a micro delegation and
you can say that ambitious delegation is
like here's the definition of my project
let me give you like one paragraph in
English go ahead develop the back end
for me the front end everything the CI
the integration and come back when
you're ready right so that's a higher
degree of autonomy. But now trust is a
little more challenging. Am I or are
you, Greg, going to sit down and review
30,000 lines of code generated by AI and
make sure that they did what you wanted
in the spec? Does your spec even cover
all the kind of twists and turns of the
possible implementation? And so that
continuum like going from the micro
specification with the very tight human
in the loop trust with kind of common
sense judgment all the way to high level
spec and somehow establishing trust on
that. I think that journey is
interesting and and that's what we're
doing. I really like that concept of a
micro delegation all the way up to a
macro delegation. I think that's really
helpful. Thanks for sharing that idea.
Yeah, I think really the future is every
engineer is really a team lead and that
team lead is leading a team of AI
engineers. They could be specialized in
different domains. The AI engineers,
they could have varying expertise, but I
think every engineer would have to start
thinking like an engineering manager in
a sense or at least like a team lead. H
that's a great concept. Thanks for
sharing that idea. One of the things I
heard you mention a moment ago is the
idea of review. Does Tab 9 have features
that would help me as an engineer to
support automated code review for like a
pull requests on GitHub? Yeah. Yeah. Top
9 does what we call top 9 coaching which
is organization specific code review. So
code review is really a challenging
problem, right? you've been around as an
expert on these areas of software
engineering and you know that code
review is really challenging first and
foremost on like hey what is even good
code and what are valuable comments and
what is just pure noise right I mean do
I want the AI to give comments about hey
Greg use more meaningful variable names
maybe do I want comments hey your
function has whatever cyclatic IC
complexity 15 and you should refactor it
to be lower maybe. Not sure that these
are like the super high value comments
that I expect from AI, right? What I
want AI to do is to give me comments
that are thoughtful about the meaningful
parts of the code. Hey, hey, Greg, you
are sending customer data without
encryption here. That's actually
valuable, right? That's a comment that I
would like to get not something that you
may have division by zero again division
by zero is great and valuable but there
are many other ways llinters and you
know static analysis tools that I've
worked on for many years that can give
you that but kind of the meaningful
things of like hey you're handling the
database connection in a way that may be
leaking your credentials or something
like that these are the meaningful
comments I look for in code view sorry
but I went off a tangent what I wanted
to say initially
is that what top man lets you do is to
define organization specific rules of
what does it mean to have quality code
and like what do you consider quality
code right so you can say hey you know
in my project we only serve our files
from Google cloud storage so if you're
doing something else that serves files
from another source maybe that's correct
technically but it's not appropriate for
my project so you can define these rules
You can have Top N check them. You can
have Top N learn them from past code
reviews and code history. So, it's
really a very powerful module and I'm
really really excited by it and excited
by the key role that it plays moving
forward to the AI engineer because as I
said when moving to the AI engineer when
moving the delegation boundary to more
code being generated by silicon by I you
need to somehow scale the question of
trust or the problem of trust. How can
we trust whatever it is that is being
generated by these agents? So code
review is central to that question.
Later we'll talk about trust when it
comes to the specific models that tab 9
has generated. But in the context of
code review I'm wondering does tab 9
give us advice and do the code review in
the IDE like in PyCharm or in Jet Brains
or does it do it inside of GitHub? Where
does the code review actually take
place? Yeah, so we have code review in
the pull request. So you can do that in
GitHub, GitLab, Bitbucket, wherever you
work. So Tub9's philosophy is to meet
the developers wherever they work. And
so we have that integration already with
the main source code platforms as I
mentioned. And also I think very soon
it's going to be in the ID as well.
There's a CLI that you can invoke from
your CI process and get the results in
whatever format you'd like. Again, the
idea is to have the same engine power
all these integrations and have
developers consume the results of the
code review wherever they need it. That
sounds really interesting. So, there's a
tab 9 CLI that I can run in my terminal
window and then is it the case that I
can also run it in GitHub actions and
then it comments on the pull request
there? Yeah, exactly right. Okay, that
sounds really awesome. Now, it's clearly
the case that Tab 9 is providing
features in PyCharm or Jet Brains or
Neoim. And I see you have a lot of
different plugins and now I've learned
that you can also integrate with the CLI
or into things like GitHub actions. So,
how did you build all of these different
interactions and integrations? Are they
all separate tools? Are they all part of
one Tab 9 binary? How was the system
actually built? Oh, in terms of
architecture, I think first of all, ID
integration is really challenging. IDEs
are plenty and they move pretty quickly
in ways that are often not very
backwards compatible. So, the APIs are
Yeah, you've seen these things. So
really our design goal from the start
was to keep the ID integration really as
a sort of a shell and have the engine
outside the IDE. So Tub9 is architected
as a central engine binary which is
written in Rust by the way that powers
all of Tub 9's functionality and the
various ID plugins are all talking to
this single binary and the binary does
all the heavy lifting of all the
interesting tasks. So you mentioned
architecture a moment ago. Let's dwell
there and then I want to talk more about
why you picked Rust in order to build
Tab 9. But first of all, from an
architectural standpoint, I'm guessing
that there are parts of Tab 9 that run
on the developer workstation and then
maybe other parts that run in the cloud.
Can you kind of explain how that works
in Tab 9? Yeah, so first of all, yes,
there's obviously kind of the local
interaction, integration with IDE,
plugins, awareness of the current
project, what is going on in terms of
existing code, a new workspace, etc.,
etc. semantic analysis of the codebase.
All of that is happening locally on your
machine and top 9 maintains some
representation of your code base
locally. So it can use that as part of
the top 9 context engine. Right? So when
you are doing something like generating
new code, top 9 is aware of your
existing code. When you're doing code
completion, top 9 is aware of similar
code that already exists in your
codebase. when you're asking to generate
tests, you know, top 9 knows the
existing tests in your codebase already.
All those things are happening on the
client machine. So there's some indexing
and analysis, embedding, vector
database. All the components that you'd
imagine that exist in something like Tab
9 are running on the client. And of
course there's a server side to the
context engine that is for example
creating the representation of all the
code in the organization creating a
presentation of non-code sources of
information like jira tickets like
confluence pages other sources of
information and that part sits on the
server and obviously the two communicate
in addition there's the LM inference
itself which runs server side because
this requires GPUs for the most part,
etc. Dub9 does have a way to run models
locally, but we've been kind of
increasingly moving away from that for
the general LMS. There are some models
that may be running locally still, and
we kind of play with moving models
around based on tradeoffs of, you know,
compute and latency and others, but
generally inference is happening mostly
on the cloud these days on server side.
Okay, that's really helpful. I noticed
you talked about something called
semantic analysis and you mentioned that
there's these various analyses that are
running locally on the computer that the
developer is using. Can you say a little
bit about what semantic analysis is and
why Tab 9 needs to perform that task?
Yeah, sure. It's actually quite
interesting and cute. I like it. As part
of the context engine, when you are
performing certain tasks, you need to
know what are the available semantic
entities that you can rely on. So the
the most trivial example is let's say
I'm in Python and I'm importing certain
modules, right? Top 9 needs to know what
does it mean to import a module and
where that other module exists. In Java
is maybe even a stronger example. You
are importing things from libraries. Top
9 needs to know what is the signature of
functions in the library. Right? So it
generates code that matches signature
type signature as defined in the
library. And for that you need to
understand the notion of import. You
need to understand where is the library.
You need to analyze the structure of the
library. You need to actually have some
representation of the signatures in the
library. And you need to do that even
when you don't have the source code
available which is typical for Java. So
in Java often you get some jar files
that are the libraries, right? You don't
have the source code for that and you
still need tab 9 to generate code that
is correct to those signatures and in
order to do that you need to do some
sort of semantic analysis, understand
the dependencies, etc., etc. It's not as
drilled as it sounds. So there is a tab
9 program implemented in Rust. It's
running on my developer workstation.
It's doing things like semantic analysis
and we'll talk more about how it's
building up this program context. But
just to make sure I understood you
correctly, I think you're saying that
tab 9 works across multiple programming
languages. Is that true? Yeah. Yeah, it
works across Yeah. Most programming
languages that or mainstream programming
languages supports 80, but not all of
them have the same level of
sophistication in the semantic analysis
etc etc. All major languages have pretty
deep semantic analysis. But yeah, this
varies by language. So definitely I
wouldn't say that we support you know
Java, TypeScript, Python, JavaScript in
the same level that we support Lua,
right? So I think you can imagine that
the major languages have much better
support in terms of the semantic
analysis and other things. Yeah. So this
is a really interesting point and I
think it moves us into the next phase of
our discussion because what I'm
understanding is that tab 9 needs to be
able to represent program source code
for Java and for Python and for
JavaScript. So do you have some kind of
internal representation in tab 9 that
abstracts away from different languages?
So depends on the language. For some of
them we have something but for the most
part I've worked quite a bit on static
analysis and program representations
that are you know a based and otherwise
and deeper than that. We try not to
reinvent the wheel there but use
existing representations for most
things. Maybe the most interesting thing
there in terms of representation is sort
of dependence graph some dependence
edges between important entities in the
program but not fine grained
representations beyond dependence graphs
and as that's I think the important bits
there obviously you know we do have the
embeddings of the code base with know
vector database that in which represent
piece of code based on their embedding
and we can do nearest state neighbor
search in order to find relevant pieces
of code for particular queries etc. So
that obviously exists but in terms of
the semantic representation itself you
can think of those as additional edges
over points in the vector database. Does
that make sense? Yeah, that makes a lot
of sense. I'm catching what you're
saying. And I do in a moment want to
make sure that we define things like a
dependence graph and an a. But before we
do that, if I could jump back 10
minutes, can you briefly comment again
on why you picked Rust for the
implementation of Tab 9? Yeah. So, it's
a historical choice. I think it was not
done by me. It was done by the original
developer of Tab 9. Tab 9 which was 2019
I think. And the choice was always made
to be crossplatform and cross arc
deployment to make those things easy.
It's unfortunately quite hard to deploy
to different OSS and different
architecture in most languages without
carrying over a huge runtime and Rust
solves for that problem. Originally we
were also doing a lot of very clever
inference on the local machine. So that
requires low-level work with CPU
intrinsics and stuff like that. And then
the choice is either really C++ or Rust
and you know it's choose your poison
basically right each has I used to do a
lot of C++ so I prefer Rust to C++ as
well but I don't want to get into that
particular religious war here. Yeah.
Yeah. What you're saying makes a lot of
sense. Thanks for giving us those
details. Now, also I heard you say a
little while ago that Tab 9's Rustbased
program is creating an A and a
dependence graph. Can you explain both
of those for our listeners? Yeah. So
again, let me recap a bit for the
audience. So when we represent programs,
we would like to know something that is
a little more structured than just the
program text. For that we parse the
programs based on the grammar of the
programming language. We create a
representation that is called an
abstract syntax tree. The abstract
syntax tree you can think about that as
a compact representation of a piece of
code that abstracts away a lot of the
details but keeps the essence. So you
can have some three structured
representation of a function and inside
the function the different blocks of the
function. Inside each block you can say
hey is your conditional block or is this
a while loop or whatever it is and so it
gives you a structured representation a
treebased structured representation of a
program in a way that can be unified
also across different programming
languages. So once you have the grammar
of a program language, you can use
something like tritter or another parser
to get an abstract syntax tree for the
program and that makes a lot of
operations on programs much easier to
perform right than just performing it on
text. So that was the abstract syntax
tree part. I think the other thing that
we mention is dependence graphs and
again not going too deep on what those
means but you can say something like hey
I am calling a function fu and that
function fu is defined elsewhere and so
let me create some edge in my graph in
like a larger program graph between the
use of the function fu and the
declaration of the function fu and
similarly you can create dependencies is
between variables, between functions,
between all sorts of entities in the
code. Maybe one class inheriting from
another. You get the intuitive idea that
entities are related in some way and
you'd like to capture those
relationships. So you can use them when
for example creating context for an LLM
based operation.
Okay, thanks for that response. Now very
quickly you mentioned something called a
tree sitter parser. Can you briefly say
what a tree sitter parser is and how
that works? Treesitter is just a name of
a project from GitHub for parser
generator. Actually, it's a really
really nice project. They provide a
bunch of parsers for most languages and
a way to create parser for your favorite
language as well. And they have a lot of
utilities that allow you to do that
quickly and conveniently. It's a really
really nice project that I think the
academic audience if not already aware
of should really be made aware of and
used in the research whoever is doing PL
research at least. Thanks for that
pointer. That's awesome. Now what I want
to do is leave the land of code and jump
into the land of non-code. If I'm
understanding correctly, Tab 9 somehow
knows how to incorporate design
documents and issue tracker tickets. Can
you explain more about how Tab 9 manages
those diverse sources of data? Yeah,
we're just in the beginning of that
journey, but that journey is really
important to us in the sense of as I
said when you think about the levels of
delegation and the future of the AI
engineer, we see a lot of shifting left
beyond the ID into the higher or further
left in the process into design
documents, right? you will write the
jura ticket, hit a button and get the
implementation to a large degree, right?
And so it's important to establish these
connections and relationships early in
the evolution of the AI engineer. And so
this is what we've been doing right now.
What type 9 allows you to do allows you
to take a juro ticket and say operate on
it as additional context for whatever it
is that you're doing. So you can mention
that you're a ticket and implement it
directly in your ID which I often do and
it's quite cool. You can ask 9 to check
whether your implementation matches what
is mentioned in the Jira ticket. So you
can say hey you know what the Jira
ticket said you should have such and
such button actually your implementation
does not have that. But this is just the
beginning of the evolution here. I think
we are pushing forward on integrations
that are going beyond that like updating
the ticket for you, expanding on the
ticket for you, saying like hey the
ticket is missing the following details
based on what you already have in the
organization right or hey you said I
should create a button that whatever
updates employee details there is a
micros service called update employee
details defined elsewhere in the or do
you want me to use that or do you want
me to redevelop that part. Right? So and
again trying to bridge the semantic gap
between what is defined at high level in
a ticket and what already exists in the
codebase which is I think one of the
harder problems for engineers in general
right because it's hard for you to know
let's say I'm I'm a new engineer into
the organization I have no idea that you
know a micros service for getting
employee details or updating employee
detail already exists right and I may
try to reimplement that and if I use jp
or something it will give me a perfect
implementation of a new service that
does that, but I actually don't want to
regenerate a service. I already have one
that I should be using. You brought up a
good point. I think now you're
highlighting one of the distinctions
between chat GPT or anthropics cla
because tab 9 has access to this context
and so must be able to make better
decisions because it has more context.
Is that the right way to think about it?
Yeah, I think again LLMs are
commoditized and they are progressing in
tremendous space but at the end they are
the computation engine and they need to
be aware of what already exists what is
the context in which they're they're
operating right so you can think about
the LM as kind of an ignorant genius it
knows how to do many many many things
but not in in the relevant context in
which I'm operating right and you can
think about the best engineer in your
organization is someone who really knows
the nuts and bolts of how things
operate, right? He knows or she knows,
hey, that micros service depends on the
other thing and that database is there
and oh, you should actually never update
the version of that module because
something else depends on it. So they
have this representation of the entire
system in their head and they know how
things interconnect and what should be
changed together and what shouldn't be
touched etc. So that's the best engineer
in your org. So you want really to
bridge these two things make the LM as
aware of the org as your best engineer
and this is how you get like to 10x
productivity of the AI engineer right to
onboard the AI to your organization.
This is really the task here and this is
what top 9 is doing kind of onboarding
the AI to your organization in a way
that the AI engineer operates like your
best engineer. Ideally top 9 should
always be the best employee of the
month, right? employee of the month
award should go to to 9 in organization.
Thank you for that response. That was
helpful and informative. Now, in some of
the projects I've worked on, I've had
situations where the documentation
drifted from the implementation. So, how
does Tab 9 actually address the fact
that some sources of context are really
helpful and it's going to lead to it
becoming employee of the month? But
other sources are less helpful because
they like for example no longer
reference or represent the truth of the
codebase. Can you give more details
about that? Yeah, that that's definitely
a challenge. I don't want to overplay
the abilities of the AI to kind of know
what is really the best source of
information here and it is actually not
that hard to mislead the AI. So let let
me just maybe give you an anecdote from
customers right so initially whenever
you talk to customer they say hey I have
30 million lines of code and why don't I
connect top 9 to this 30 million lines
of code to inform top 9 there's
documentation there there's a bunch of
stuff as well right they want to connect
it to everything and then they say you
know what coming to think of it 27
million lines of code from this code
base actually think that no one should
ever look at that's like legacy which is
the counter for example, for what we
want to do. So, let's disconnect all
that and let's focus on the 3 million
lines. They didn't need not be the most
recent ones. By the way, initially when
when I started, I thought like, hey, we
just look at the recent stuff and that
must be the right way to do things. It's
sometimes correct, but sometimes they're
just like some golden repository,
something that is like, oh, here's like
our best work, our masterpiece, and
everything should contextualize on that
because that's the best way to do stuff,
right? things. So there's some nuance to
that and you still need some human
guidance to connect Top 9 to to the
right sources and not mislead it. And in
in particular, there is a problem with
huge legacy code bases that unless
you're careful and give extra guidance
through coaching, you may be trapped in
the kind of Jupiter level gravity of
legacy in the sense that you you will
always keep generating code that is
similar to the way you know you did
things 20 years ago, right? You will be
generating new legacy. So you don't want
that. And this is also why we created
the coaching module that allows you to
explicitly say you know what type 9
that's the way I want you to do things
right if somebody asks you to connect to
a database the way to do that is this
new way and not the old way right so you
can control what AI does explicitly as
the architect or as the dev manager or
as the senior engineer so it sounds like
tab 9 can first of all automatically
assess the quality of some sources but
then it will also take hints from me as
a software engineer in order to help me
to be the human in the loop to point out
what is good code or good docs. Am I
thinking about it the right way?
Absolutely. So I think again if you
think about it as onboarding the AI
engineer to the organization there are
certain things you expect the AI to
understand by itself. Hey look at this
codebase no get the gist of it. You
should just implicitly learn what's
important and topline would do that. But
certain things cannot or maybe too hard
to be learned implicitly and you want to
control them explicitly as the human in
charge, right? You want to say, "Hey, I
don't care what you learned from this
old crusty Java 8 code. We're in a
different world now and you know, here
are the rules of the new game. I'm
telling you as the architect, right?
Here are here's the way to do stuff."
When I was reading the Tab 9
documentation and checking out your blog
posts, one of the words that I noticed
you used frequently was provenence and
the other was attribution. How do
provenence and attribution play into the
tasks that Tab 9 can automatically
complete? Yeah, I think those are
important things when you are moving to
LMS that have been trained on anything
and everything out there. So, Tab 9
really cares about what we call
protection and protection means
protecting you against generating code
that potentially violates IP, right? IP
rights and we have a model called top 9
protected which has been trained only on
permissively open- source license code.
So you can pick that if you're very
protection conscious, if you're very
risk averse in terms of IP, you can
always pick topline protected. But as
external models become more and more
powerful and want to enable those for
our customers and give them the freedom
of choice without having to worry about
protection. Well, we provide provenence
and attribution or what we call also
inference time protection meaning that
we have recitation checks and basically
matching any code that is generated by
Tub9 against all of the code out there
in some abstraction and letting you
know, hey Greg, you know what, this
piece of code is really similar to the
Linux kernel which is licensed under
GPL2, right? So, hey, do you want to
take that? Do you want to your
developers in the organization to not
even see code of this flavor? Maybe you
want to only suggest code that is MIT or
Apache license. So provenence encryption
lets you find kind of the the origins of
the code being generated in case it is
very similar to something else out there
and it does that at inference time
almost near real time and you can
configure the behavior as I said to even
block those things from being presented
to your developers. So the top 9 is I
did not mention that earlier but top 9
is like an enterprise first AI
assistant. So we really care about
privacy about protection about
personalization to the enterprise. So
all those things like privacy protection
and personalization are the things that
make top 9 great for for the enterprise.
Okay that makes sense. I remember
earlier in our conversation you
mentioned that trust was central to tab
9 and now I'm understanding that
inference time protection is one of the
key ways to make sure there's trust
between the software engineer and the
tab 9 system yeah in some sense
protection is one facet of that when I
talk about trust when when I said trust
earlier I meant more on the functional
side of things more in the sense of like
hey you ask me to generate whatever
something that connects to a database
and gets all employee records. Can I
trust that what I got is actually
reading all employee records? Or maybe
due to a pageionation error, you only
got the first 100 and you did not
pageionate through the tape, right? Like
these subtle bugs or hey, maybe you
asked me to read all employee records
and I did not know that they are across
three different tables for whatever
reasons, right? And I only got you one
of them, right? So these kind of
functional things that I have to worry
about when I delegate a task, this is
what I talk when when I mean when I say
trust. Thanks for that clarification.
That was really helpful. In a moment, I
want to chat about Tab 9 and how it can
help with things like automated test
data generation. But before I do that, I
thought it would be helpful if you could
briefly comment on the different
cloud-based LLMs that you can integrate
in with Tab 9. Can you share more
details with our listeners? Yeah,
absolutely. So, Tub9 is always trying to
bring the best models out there to our
users and as such we offer all the know
latest greatest models from Anthropic,
Open AAI, Google etc. So, you can get
Gemini, you can get Claude Sonet 3.5,
you can get GPT4, you can get all of
these models. Again the pace of
innovation on these with new reasoning
models and others is really really fast.
We are always going to bring the best
out there to to our customer whatever
matches their deployment restrictions
their preferred cloud provider and maybe
protection requirements. So our goal is
really to work with the customer to see
what are the requirements in term of
privacy and protection and preference to
cloud provider and model abilities and
provide that. You know as of today we
find in our internal benchmarks that
cloud set is is the best right now but
Google is having a very strong showing
with the le latest Gemini and these
things change constantly. So we give our
customers the freedom to just switch
between these models completely
seamlessly. It used to be the case that
different models did had different
performance across different tasks. So
maybe one model is better for code
review, another is better for test
generation and another is better for
code generation. Right now it looks like
claude is doing the best on all of them.
But yeah, some open source models are
also performing really well. latest
llama 3.3 I know the latest QN family
and others. Yeah, actually that's a
really interesting point and something
that I was going to discuss. So I can
configure Tab 9 when it's generating
test cases to use one model but then
perhaps configure it to pick a different
model if it's creating documentation or
doing code review. Yeah, right now we
don't offer that control at the customer
level. we decide for certain things but
you could if we find that models diverge
again in their abilities we may open
that again right right now it's just
like if you bet on claudet to do this
you're not going to be wrong right so no
need for this fine grain control on on
the customer side okay very interesting
let's talk briefly about test cases I
noticed when using tab 9 that it can
like suggest test cases to me by looking
at my code and then saying hey these 10
tests could be useful to you. So my
question is how does tab 9 decide how
many test cases to suggest to me and
then how does it decide which test cases
it thinks I will find most useful? Yeah,
there's some simple agentic flow there
that is trying to look at the existing
test and see what is missing and then
generate a test plan according to what
is missing. So that's just I think v1 of
the test agent. It kind of generates the
test plan, allows you to refine it and
then generate tests from the test plan.
The next version is, as I mentioned
earlier, something that is going to
generate code coverage target completely
automatically. So it's generating the
tests, measuring the coverage, seeing
what parts of the code are not covered,
generating additional tests, etc. until
you you reach coverage. Of course, all
of those things still require human
supervision in the sense that you want
these tests to actually be interesting
and meaningful and not, you know, cover
code in trivial ways and maybe also want
them to be meaningful tests when going
into the future, right? Only you, the
human, kind of know where you want to go
with this code base and what tests are
kind of like forwardlooking, right? So
you want still to to provide some human
guidance. But as I said because the
question of trust is so central. How can
I trust the things that are being
generated by by the AI engineer? I think
the code coverage agent and automatic
test generation are also central tenants
of what type 9 is going to do in the
future. So these agents are going to
improve tremendously and also be tied to
things that we see in code review and
things that we see in runtime etc. Okay.
So it sounds like coverage guided test
case generation is on the road map for
tab 9. Is that the right way to think
about it? It's working. It's not just on
the road map. It's not not released yet,
but it's yeah internally this is
something that we're close to deploying.
Yeah. So, does Tab 9 generate unit test
cases or integration tests or regression
tests or fuzz tests or all of those? How
does it work? No, no. Right now, mostly
unit tests and the others again we will
get there. Not quite there yet. I think
the regression is another interesting
point to intervene. But I think this is
still there's some way to go there. So
in certain cases, I've either
automatically generated a test or
written one of my own and then the test
case fails. However, I ultimately
realized it was a bug in my test case
and not a bug in my function under test.
So how does Tab 9 distinguish between a
test case that's failing because it's a
buggy test versus a test case that's
failing because it found a bug? Yeah,
obviously without an additional
specification somewhere, you you would
not know that, right? So the the thing
is you need to enter that specification
somewhere and tab 9 will check against
that. People are not that big outside
academia about writing specs really
right. So
so when tab 9 is generating these test
cases can it also generate like the mock
objects or the spies or the stubs that
it needs? Yeah it does. It does. So if
you need some mock objects etc. It would
do that again to a certain degree of
sophistication. Don't expect it to do,
you know, the level of mocking that you
did in your super duper complicated
project, right? But it will do the the
basic things. It will definitely get out
of the way. Okay, that makes a lot of
sense. Now, I noticed that when I write
test cases, sometimes my test cases
aren't good because ultimately they
prove to be flaky or sometimes they're
too tightly tied to the implementation
and they're like a change detector test,
which I would also consider low quality.
Yeah. So, does Tab 9 have guard rails in
place that help it to automatically
generate test cases that are not going
to be flaky or not going to be a change
detector? No, not yet. I think flakiness
I have not seen much, but definitely
change detection as you call it. I I
think that's definitely some bias in in
the AI because that's like kind of
overfitting to the existing
implementation and generating the test
to test that. I think that is happening.
Not exactly sure how to generalize
around that, but we'll see. Oh, these
are problems we're working on. So, if
there's a failing test case, can I give
that test case to tab 9 and have it fix
the program under test so that the test
passes? You can do that. It's not an
automatic integration yet, but you can
definitely point to it and say like
mention the test and say this is
failing. Please change the code
according to that. Yeah. Okay. So, we've
covered a lot of very cool features of
Tab 9. We talked about how it uses all
of these different forms of context and
how it can automatically generate test
cases. Are there features of tab 9 that
we haven't highlighted yet that you
wanted to draw to the attention of our
listeners? Let me see. I have to review
the things that I'm I'm using all the
time. So I think when you are working
with a chat interface for example in in
tab 9, one question is how do you
consume back the results that you get
from chat? And I think we've worked
really hard on kind of automatically
applying these changes across files and
and and things like that. That's going
to be an area of further improvement in
in tab 9. So in recent months, so I used
to work mostly with code completion
because I typically know what I'm doing
and I'm like doing very point changes in
in my code, etc. So I'm probably doing
what most would consider specialized
work in in the logic of the product and
stuff that is fairly deep and deeply
contextualized also. So I used to use
mostly code completions but in recent
months I moved to use mostly chat
because since we introduced the apply
all kind of magic which is like here's
everything that was generated just hit a
button and all the code gets changed
automatically. I started using that for
almost everything that I do and so that
apply was a leap of abilities in in tab
9 for me at least as a user and I think
the further it improves I find that I do
less code completions even for things I
know exactly how to complete maybe even
if it's a oneline change I still do it
in the chat interface and going to have
the line change whatever needs to change
in order to make it happen so habitually
I would say against my better judgment
in a sense I started using more the chat
and that's the code completion and I
imagine that and I know actually I'll
just imagine that a lot of the people
who kind of adopt AI for real like all
in are also transitioning to using more
of the chat interface than completion.
It's just again a question of habit.
Where do you go first? Right? And so I
think the habits are changing in front
of our eyes. Right? So yeah, that's a
really thoughtprovoking insight and it's
something that I have noticed in myself
and many of the other engineers with
whom I regularly chat. So thanks for
pointing out that change in developer
practice and experience. What I would
like to do now is to go back to what we
might call the roots of Tab 9. you've
actually been involved in publishing and
presenting a number of research papers
and I think some of those research
papers have actually planted the seeds
for tab 9. So there's two frameworks in
particular that I wanted to briefly chat
about. One is called code to sec and the
other is called code tovec and it's seq
and then vec and I think code stands for
source code. Can you tell us what those
other things are all about and how they
influenced the creation of Tab 9? Oh,
these are beautiful works by my former
student Urielon and Mal Zeberstein and
Shak Broady and and I think one of them
is also with other friends and
contributors like Levy from Google.
These are really wow so much time has
passed. These are circa 2018 and they're
not even or 2019 and they're not even
the first work that we've done around
code completion and these things like
code completion I think is 2012 when we
started seeing that you could do some ML
based code completion and that is really
what informed this entire line of work.
So let me talk for a second about the
specific things that you ask. code tovec
was really a very nice work on how to
represent a code for tasks like function
name completion. Maybe you could use
that also to predict names of variables
and stuff like that. So it was very very
early and straightforward use of neural
networks I would say for code specific
tasks. You can think of that also as
like the first embedder for code I would
say creating some neural representation
or dense representation of code as
vectors as dense vectors. So I think
that was 2019 that was really nice work.
So that is code tovec. It's still very
widely used because it's very simple. So
it uses basically paths in the abstract
syntax tree to represent a piece of code
and then basically compute some
embedding or some neural representation
of those paths of the combination of
paths in the so that was like the first
work that we've done around that with a
really beautiful work by Uria and I
think one year later we did code to sec
which was generating a sequence of from
a piece of code the idea that was to say
hey let's generate just like captions
for images it was captions for pieces of
code right so just generate a document
or like a line of description for a
piece of code and those were tiny tiny
neural networks this is I think neural
networks in the size of like 150 million
parameters which is like know in in
these days this sounds like something
you can I know I can probably run 100 of
those on my iPhone right so these are
like early days of work on neural
representation ations of code and I
think there has been a lot of follow on
work on that. We've done again a lot of
work following that on
adversarial examples for models of code
and all sorts of additional practical
work like how to do edit completions by
shakad. I think shed probably did very
nice work on how to predict edits rather
than to predict code completions. You
want to predict how code is going to be
edited. you made an edit in one place,
you want to predict other edits in the
same code, right? How code is being
updated as a result of change. And
there's a bunch of very nice academic
work there. I think when we did all the
academic work, the trade-offs are quite
different than what you'd like to see in
industry, right? So, academic work is
often very high accuracy, but maybe
latency is too high to be used in
practice. And maybe you know you get 10%
improvement in accuracy but at 10x
latency or 10x computational cost. And
these things again for for academic
research it makes perfect sense. And
then maybe other people find a way to
make this faster or better or cheaper.
But the tradeoff there is not something
that matches the the requirements in in
industry. So, thanks for sharing those
details about the trade-offs. For
listeners who are interested in
exploring more, we'll link them to
episodes of software engineering radio
that have also talked about generative
AI and software engineering. And in the
show notes, we'll also link to the
websites for tab 9 and code to sec and
code tovec. Thanks for giving us those
details. I'm wondering since you're both
a CTO and a professor and you've already
begun to hint at this, can you share
with us some details about how you
transition to reach search prototype
into production use? Yeah. So I think my
friends in in Microsoft research told me
many many years ago that when you
transition from a research to product
you realize that the the research part
or like the deep tech part becomes at
most 20% of of the product at the end.
So my experience has not been different.
I think there's just so much that has to
go into a product in terms of the user
experience in terms of how the product
behaves. What are the kind of latency
requirements? What are the cost
requirements? What does it mean to do
inference at scale? All those things are
things that are not super interesting
academically for the most part, but are
really really important in making things
work for real. And I think I have
tremendous appreciation for that
practical work and and for what does it
take to make a real product work in the
hands of real users, right? I think it
it's just a tremendous amount of work to
do that. In terms of the research to
kind of the academic research into
practice lens, I would say that a lot of
what people are doing these days in
knowixie or FSE or a lot of the software
engineering conferences in terms of the
ML stuff is also being done in industry
and I think not necessarily in a worse
way just people don't really write about
it right so I would say that people in
academia Yeah, my advice and what I do
myself also is academically is to think
about how this would look 10 years from
now, not one year from now because the
one year from now industry knows and
industry is already doing even if you
don't read about it in in a research
paper right and so it's not an easy
task. So I I'm it's hard to imagine you
know 10 years from now how things would
look but trying to imagine and trying to
imagine a completely different world of
how people program is what I expect
academic research to bring to the table.
Doing prompt engineering for you know
code review. Sure you can do some
research about that and it's
interesting. It's not a solved problem
in any sense, but I think industry is
working on that and industry will solve
it in a way that is maybe not the most
interesting, but definitely the most
working and practical. I think that's
the the balance that I'd expect like for
to look further out and some people are
definitely doing that as well. Thanks.
As we draw this episode of Software
Engineering Radio to conclusion, I'm
wondering, do you have a call for action
to our listeners who are software
engineers working in practice and may
want to try to effectively apply
generative AI tools like Tab 9? Yeah,
you know, it's the obvious advice, I
guess, but just play with it. No, lean
in. Adopt these tools. They are not
going away. This is how things are going
to be. In some way, resistance is futile
and you should lean in. See what works
for you. Not everything works the same
way. Have realistic expectations. This
is not some magical thing that will make
all your work go away and will
definitely won't replace you. So lean
in, see what works for you and adopt it.
I think realistically speaking, you can
automate a lot of the kind of simple
things, right? which should give you
more time to focus on the work that you
want to do anyway which is the creative
work and you know the deep algorithmic
maybe or innovative work parts of of
your job. It is interesting to also see
the evolution of how the code base how
your code base should evolve to make
AI's life easier. So if you think of how
top 9 works by contextualizing on the
entire codebase and you know that it is
doing some retmented generation that is
based both on semantic and non semantic
similarities and embeddings and stuff
like that. You can think about you know
adding maybe a bit more documentation to
your existing codebase. maybe changing
the names of functions to be and
parameters to be slightly more
meaningful such that both future humans
and future AIs can make better use of
the codebase. And I think these things
are things to think about as you design
a system for the future and as you
refactor code for the future is not like
how do I make it easier for future
humans but also for the future AI
systems that are going to want to
leverage that. I think people who are
going to build their codebase this way
are going to have better productivity
multiplier from AI based tools. H that's
a really interesting insight and a great
call to action for our listeners. Aaron,
thanks for taking time to chat with us
on software engineering radio. This has
really been an awesome conversation. Oh,
thank you so much for having me. I
enjoyed every minute. Thank you.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by it
e software magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at
se-radio.net. To provide feedback, you
can comment on each episode on the
website or reach us on LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack
channel at
seradio.slack.com. You can also email us
at teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.